Sadhna didi: She used to travel so much, I mean, that was a time when I was not so
साधना दीदी : वह(श्री माताजी) इतना सफ़र करती थीं, मेरा मतलब है, वह एक समय था जब मैं
much with Her because I was in my home and She was in Europe and She used to Bulgaria,
बहुत उनके साथ नहीं थी क्योंकि मैं अपने घर में थी और वह यूरोप में थीं, और वह जातीं थीं कभी बुल्गारिया,
Romania, I'm hearing She's here, there. She went to South America. How She managed, I tell you,
रोमानिया, मैं सुनती थी वह यहाँ हैं, वहाँ हैं। वह दक्षिण अमेरिका गयीं। वह कैसे प्रबंधित करतीं थीं, मैं कहूँ,
I can't tell you this! Lately, I was travelling more with Her. We went to Dubai
मैं आपको यह नहीं बता सकती! हाल ही में, मैं उनके साथ अधिक यात्रा करने लगी। हम दुबई गए
and, while leaving the leader of Dubai collective, he was sitting like this,
और वहां से चलते समय, दुबई की सामूहिकता के नेता, इस तरह बैठे थे,
very quiet. We said, "What's happened?" He said, "You know didi, now that Mother
बहुत शांत। हमने कहा, "क्या हुआ?" उन्होंने कहा, "आप जानतीं हैं दीदी, अब जो माँ
is going out of my hands, I'm feeling sad." So, I told that to somebody else who
पास से जा रहीं हैं मुझे बहुत उदासी लग रही है।" तो, मैंने यह बात किसी और को बताई जो
was also, like this, feeling sad because She was leaving from another place. I said,
भी, इसी तरह, उदासी महसूस कर रहा था, क्योंकि वह दूसरी जगह से जा रहीं थीं। मैंने कहा,
"You know, this is like a cycle and Mother leaves and departs and the people behind
"आपको पता है, यह एक चक्र की तरह है और माँ जब छोड़कर प्रस्थान करतीं हैं और पीछे रह जाने वाले लोग
are feeling sad and Mother is sad too to say, bye and then She's getting ready to
उदास महसूस कर रहे हैं और माँ भी उदास हैं, अलविदा कहने में, और फिर वह तैयार हो रहीं हैं,
arrive with a lot of smiling faces waiting for Her - She goes from there to there."
इंतजार करते हुए, ढेर सारे मुस्कुराते चेहरों से मिलने के लिए - वह वहाँ से वहाँ जातीं हैं।"
Though everybody asked Me this that, "How, how could you, you know, as a Mother share Her?"
हालांकि सभी ने मुझसे यह पूछा कि, "कैसे, आप कैसे अपनी माँ को औरों के साथ साझा कर सकीं?"
and of course you, you're as a child you want your Mother all the time, it's natural.
और निश्चित रूप से, यह स्वाभाविक है कि, आप एक औलाद के रूप में, अपनी माँ को हर समय अपने पास चाहोगे।
But then She timed it as such when, I think, I was engaged to be married already
लेकिन फिर, उन्होंने ऐसा काल चुना, जब मेरे विचार से, मेरी सगाई हो चुकी थी शादी होने के लिए।
once She was... It was 1970, right? That is the date, so I was already engaged to
एक बार वह थीं ... यह 1970 था, है ना? यह ही तारीख है, तो मेरी पहले ही सगाई हो चुकी थी
be married, my sister was already married, so as they say, Her worldly duties were, kind of over.
शादी होने के लिए। मेरी बहन पहले से शादीशुदा थी, जैसा कि कहते हैं, उनके सांसारिक कर्तव्य, एक तरह से पूरे हो चुके थे।
Kalpana didi: I never found it very different except, you know, when I saw Her
कल्पना दीदी: मुझे कभी फर्क नहीं महसूस हुआ सिवाय इसके कि, आप जानते हैं, जब मैंने उनके
posters all over and I said, "Oh, my God!" so, She sort of, She became renowned
चारों तरफ पोस्टर देखे, तो मैं बोली, "अरे भगवान!" तो वह, एक तरह से, प्रसिद्ध हो गयीं
all over the world but to me always a Mother.
पूरी दुनिया में, लेकिन मेरे लिए वह हमेशा एक माँ।
Sadhna didi: Ho, She was a strong Mother, very strong and She was, She was very keen on,
साधना दीदी: हो, वह एक सबल माँ थीं, बहुत सबल थीं और वह बहुत उत्सुक थीं,
you know, we were being correct and right and very dharmic, you know that, that emphasis was
आप जानते हैं, कि हम दोष रहित और सही तथा बहुत धार्मिक रहें। आप जानते हैं कि, यह जोर था
very strong, that you must never do anything wrong and it was easier in those days
कि हम बहुत मजबूत हों, कि हमें कभी कुछ गलत नहीं करना चाहिए और उन दिनों यह आसान भी था
because, I think, dishonesty was not at all a common thing. So you had to live
क्योंकि, मुझे लगता है, उन दिनों बेईमानी बिलकुल भी एक आम बात नहीं थी। तो आपको जीना था
within your budget. So, automatically, you became a kind of person and you know,
अपने बजट में। तो, स्वचालित रूप से, आप एक प्रकार के व्यक्ति बन गए, और आप जानते हैं,
attention did not go on to many luxuries. Also we did not have consumerism in those
बहुत सारी विलासिता की ओर ध्यान नहीं गया। साथ ही उन दिनों उपभोक्तावाद भी नहीं था,
days, I mean, we lived simply.
मेरा मतलब है, हम सादगी से रहते थे।
The majority of people were of the same type of thinking. It was not so difficult,
अधिकांश लोग उसी प्रकार की सोच के थे। इतना कठिन नहीं था,
you didn't have peer pressure, most of the girls were being brought up well, you know
आप पर साथियों का दबाव नहीं था, इनमें से अधिकांश लड़कियों को अच्छी तरह से पाला जा रहा था। आप जानते हैं,
Also, I don't think there was that much of conflict in generations -
साथ ही, मुझे नहीं लगता, कि पीढ़ियों में बहुत संघर्ष था -
- it was more flowing - you know, family used to flow well.
- यह एक बहाव की तरह था - आपको पता है, परिवार अच्छा चलता था।